<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The beauty of holines: or The consecration of a house of prayer, by the example of our Sauiour A sermon preached in the chappell at the free-schoole in Shrewsbury. the 10. day of September, Anno Dom. 1617. At the consecration of the chappell, by the Right Reuerend Father in God, the Lord Bishop of Couentrey and Lichfield. By Sampson Price, Doctor in Diuinity, and chapleine in ordinary to his Maiesty.</title>
            <author>Price, Sampson, 1585 or 6-1630.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1618</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10073</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20328</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100873</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836700</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836700</idno>
            <idno type="VID">986</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10073)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 986)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1183:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The beauty of holines: or The consecration of a house of prayer, by the example of our Sauiour A sermon preached in the chappell at the free-schoole in Shrewsbury. the 10. day of September, Anno Dom. 1617. At the consecration of the chappell, by the Right Reuerend Father in God, the Lord Bishop of Couentrey and Lichfield. By Sampson Price, Doctor in Diuinity, and chapleine in ordinary to his Maiesty.</title>
                  <author>Price, Sampson, 1585 or 6-1630.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 37, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by B[ernard]: A[lsop]: for Richard Meighen, and are to be solde at his shop neere S. Clements Church without Temple-Barre,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1618.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Some pages marked and stained.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:986:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:986:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE BEAVTY OF HOLINES: <hi>OR</hi> THE CONSECRATION of a Houſe of Prayer, by the <hi>Example of our Sauiour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Sermon Preached in the Chappell at the Free-<hi>Schoole in Shrewsbury. the</hi> 10. <hi>day of</hi> September, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1617.</p>
            <p>At the Conſecration of the Chappell, by the Right <hi>Reuerend Father in God, the Lord Biſhop of</hi> Couentrey and Lichfield.</p>
            <p>BY SAMPSON PRICE, Doctor in Diuinity, and <hi>Chapleine in Ordinary to his Maieſty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Imprinted by <hi>B: A:</hi> for <hi>Richard Meighen,</hi> and are to be ſolde at his Shop neere S. Clements Church without Temple-Barre. 1618.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:986:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:986:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT Worſhipfull, <hi>the</hi> Bailiues <hi>of</hi> Shrewsbury, <hi>the</hi> 12. Aldermen, <hi>the</hi> 24. Counſellours, <hi>toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the other</hi> Members <hi>of that flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing</hi> Corporation: Grace, Mercy <hi>and</hi> Peace <hi>bee multiplied vnto you from</hi> GOD.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">K</seg>Ing Solomon</hi> began to build his <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> in the moneth <hi>April</hi> or <hi>Zif,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vatablus,</hi> and the Chaldee Paraphraſe.</note> when <hi>flowres</hi> open; and finiſhed it in the moneth <hi>Bul,</hi> when <hi>hearbes</hi> beginne to cloſe vp and wither, anſwerable to our <hi>December:</hi> This <hi>Sermon</hi> was preached among you in the beginning of <hi>Winter,</hi> and ſince hath been <hi>ſhut</hi> vp yet now vpon the importunity of ſome friends commeth to <hi>life</hi> againe, with the beginning of the <hi>Spring,</hi> My warning for it was ſhort, and being then in the <hi>Country</hi> with you to ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my <hi>labours</hi> among you according to my <hi>promiſe,</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon your free <hi>grant</hi> of a worthy <hi>fauour</hi> vnto mee; I was conſtrained to vſe onely the helpe of my <hi>deare</hi> and <hi>Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Fathers Library:</hi> Your former acceptance of my
<pb facs="tcp:986:3"/>
               <hi>paines</hi> aſſure me, that I ſhall not be <hi>miſconſtrued</hi> in this <hi>labour,</hi> which I vndertooke out of that <hi>loue</hi> I owe vnto you all and yours. Many things in themſelues of no <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plinie.</note> haue beene <hi>highly</hi> prized, becauſe they haue beene <hi>dedicated</hi> to <hi>Temples.</hi> This ſudden <hi>Sermon</hi> I hope ſhal finde <hi>acceptance,</hi> becauſe it was <hi>dedicated</hi> at the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration</hi> of your little <hi>Temple.</hi> Your <hi>Schoole</hi> foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by gracious King <hi>Edward,</hi> a <hi>Prince</hi> of bleſſed memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; and confirmed <hi>by Q. Elizabeth,</hi> a <hi>Princeſſe</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy neuer to be forgotten, for loue to the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> ſtill <hi>flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth,</hi> and <hi>long may it:</hi> yet neuer was conſecrated till now. <hi>Continue</hi> your <hi>care</hi> of it: your <hi>loue</hi> to the <hi>church,</hi> and <hi>reſpect</hi> of thoſe who are <hi>inſtruments</hi> to inſtruct you in the way to <hi>Heauen; So</hi> ſhall you <hi>continue</hi> thoſe many <hi>bleſſings,</hi> which already you enioy; and <hi>multiplie</hi> them for your <hi>poſterity, which</hi> I ſhall <hi>pray</hi> for; and <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour</hi> by all <hi>Chriſtian reſpects,</hi> which I may <hi>performe</hi> vnto you.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From my <hi>Study</hi> in <hi>London:</hi> 
                  <date>April. <hi>5. 1617.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours in the</hi> Lord, <hi>in all faithfull</hi> obſeruance, <hi>SAMPSON PRICE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:986:3"/>
            <head>THE BEAVTY OF HOLINESSE.</head>
            <head type="sub">Lord Ieſu, begin and end.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>IOHN X. XXII. XXIII.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>And it was at Hieruſalem, the Feaſt of the Dedication, and it was winter, and Ieſus walked in the Temple in Salomons Porch.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN King <hi>Salomon,</hi> that mirrour of Wiſedome, Vnderſtanding, Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and Honour (ſo that there was <hi>None like him</hi> before him, neither after him ſhall any ariſe like vnto him, 1.<hi>King.</hi> 3) had rayſed a leuie out of all <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. King. 3.12.</note> of thirty thouſand men to fetch Cedars from Lebanon, <hi>threeſcore</hi> and ten thouſand to beare burthens, <hi>foureſcore</hi> thouſand hewers in the mountaines, <hi>and</hi> three thouſand and three hundred, which ruled ouer the people that wrought in the worke, 1. <hi>King.</hi> 5.<note place="margin">1. King. 5.16.1. 1. Ring. 6. 2. Chr. 3, 1.</note> In the foure hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth &amp; foureſcorth yeere after the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were come out of the land of Egypt, <hi>hee</hi> beganne to build the houſe of the <hi>Lord</hi> at Ieruſalem in Mount Moriah:<note place="margin">Aquila, <hi>of</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oorth, Light: Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Myrrhe Raah; <hi>to ſee.</hi>
               </note> where the Lord appeared vnto <hi>Dauid</hi> his Father, a place ſo called (ſayth <hi>Aquila</hi>) of ſhining,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:986:4"/>becauſe there was the Oracle of <hi>God:</hi> or of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance of <hi>myrrhe,</hi> which was there as <hi>Oleaſter</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riueth it: or more fitly it was ſo called of <hi>ſeeing,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there the Lord was ſeene of <hi>Abraham,</hi> when the Ramme was offered by him in ſtead of his Son, <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.13;<note place="margin">Gen. 22.13.</note> and <hi>the Lord foreſaw that there his Temple ſhould bee built.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Damaſt. l. <hi>2.</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Ortho. l c. <hi>14 Gen. 8.4.</hi>
               </note> Vpon a Mountaine <hi>Paradiſe</hi> was ſituated: the <hi>Arke</hi> reſted vpon the mountains of <hi>Ararat, Gen.</hi> 8. <hi>Lot</hi> was commanded to eſcape to the mountaine, leſt he ſhould be conſumed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 10. Vpon a Mount the <hi>Law</hi> was giuen,<note place="margin">Gen. 19.17. Exod. 19 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Exod.</hi> 19. <hi>Chriſt</hi> is deſcribed by the Church to come, leaping vpon the mountaines, <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. <hi>He was tempted</hi> vpon a mountaine,<note place="margin">Chap. 2.8.</note> 
               <hi>Math.</hi> 4. <hi>Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> vpon a mountaine, <hi>Math.</hi> 5.1. wrought <hi>Miracles</hi> vpon a mountaine,<note place="margin">Mat 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.29. Ordained the <hi>twelue</hi> vpon a mountaine, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.13.14. <hi>Departed</hi> to a mountaine, when by force they would haue made him a King, <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.15. <hi>Conferde</hi> with the woman on a mountaine, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.20. <hi>Prayed</hi> on a mountaine all night, <hi>Luc.</hi> 6.12. Celebrated h s laſt <hi>Supper</hi> in a large vpper roome, <hi>Luc.</hi> 22.12, which <hi>Ambroſe</hi> placeth on a mountaine,<note place="margin">Amb. l. <hi>10.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Was <hi>crucified</hi> on mount Caluarie, <hi>Luc.</hi> 23.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Appeared</hi> to his Diſciples after his reſurrection vpon a Mount, <hi>Math.</hi> 28.16. <hi>Aſcended</hi> into heauen from a mount, <hi>Act.</hi> 19.12. and therefore appointed his <hi>Temple</hi> to be built vpon a mount. His <hi>Foundation</hi> is in the holy mountaines, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 87.1: The firſt ground of his Temple. Hee will bee <hi>worſhipped</hi> at his holy hill, <hi>Pſal,</hi> 99.9. A hill which hee deſireth to dwell in, yea the Lord will dwell in it for euer, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 68; which <hi>Salomon</hi> truely acknowledged at the feaſt of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:986:4"/>dedication of the Temple, where were the Elders of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and all the heads of the Tribes, the chiefe of the Fathers of the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and all the Congregation, ſacrificing ſheepe and oxen, that could not be numbred, &amp; the glory of the Lord filled the houſe in a cloud. He had made a <hi>brazen Scaffold,</hi> and ſet it in the midſt of the Court, and kneeling downe vpon his knees before all the Congregation, hee ſpreade forth his hands towards <hi>heauen,</hi> and ſayde; <hi>Haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the prayer of thy ſeruant,</hi> that thine eyes may be open vpon this <hi>houſe</hi> day and night, vpon the <hi>place,</hi> whereof thou haſt ſayd, that thou wouldſt put thy name there. <hi>Ariſe O Lord God into thy reſting place,</hi> 2. Chr. 6. For howſoeuer as <hi>Proſper</hi> ſpeaketh:<note place="margin">2. Chr. 6, 13, 20.41. <hi>Proſper. ex Aug.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Volens in templo orare, in te ora: &amp; ita ſemper age, vt Dei templum ſis:</hi> Art thou willing to pray in a Temple, pray within thy ſelfe, and ſo ſtill carry thy ſelfe, that thou mayeſt bee a Temple. <hi>Howſoeuer</hi> Heauen, and the Heauen of Heauens cannot containe him, much leſſe ſuch a houſe. <hi>Howbeit</hi> the moſt <hi>High</hi> dwelleth not in tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples made with hands,<note place="margin">2. Ch,. 16.18. Act. 7.48.</note> Act. 7. and that prophecie is fulfilled which <hi>Chriſt</hi> deliuered to the woman of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria,</hi> when he was a fruitfull <hi>bough by a well.</hi> Yee ſhal neyther in this mountaine,<note place="margin">Gen. 49, 22, <hi>Ioſeph. in Ant.</hi> 41. <hi>c.</hi> 7.</note> nor yet in <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the <hi>Father,</hi> that is neyther in <hi>Gerizim,</hi> where the <hi>Samaritanes</hi> built a Temple out of a proud aemulation of the <hi>Iewes;</hi> neyther at <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> the glory of the World: <hi>For God is a Spirit, and they that worſhippe him, muſt worſhippe him in Spirit and Truth,</hi> Iohn, 4 <hi>Loco non coneluditur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.24.</note> Hee is not ſhutte vp in place: When we thinke vpon his <hi>dwelling,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theoph.</note> wee muſt remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:986:5"/>(ſayth <hi>Aug:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>57.</hi>
               </note>) the congregation of <hi>Saints</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in <hi>Heauen:</hi> where God is ſayd to dwell, becauſe there his <hi>will</hi> is perfectly done,<note place="margin">1 Kin. 8 43.</note> where there is perfect <hi>obedience:</hi> yet <hi>his next habitation is his Church</hi> vpon earth, a dreadfull place, none other but the <hi>houſe</hi> of God,<note place="margin">Gen. 28.17. Iſ. 56.7.</note> and <hi>gate</hi> of heauen, <hi>Gen.</hi> 28. A houſe of <hi>Prayer</hi> for all people. <hi>Iſ.</hi> 56. Whereupon <hi>Dauid</hi> reaſoned: I dwel in an houſe of <hi>Cedar:</hi> but the <hi>Arke</hi> of God dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth within <hi>Curtaines,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 7.2.</note> purpoſing to build an houſe to the Lord God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but he was inhibited by <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than,</hi> becauſe he had ſhedde bloud aboundantly, and made great warres,<note place="margin">1 Ch. 22, 8</note> 1. <hi>Chr.</hi> 22. yet in his trouble hee <hi>prepared</hi> for the houſe of the Lord, <hi>a hundreth thouſand talents of gold,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Ch. 22.14.</note> 
               <hi>a thouſand thouſand talents of ſiluer,</hi> and of <hi>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſſe</hi> and <hi>yron</hi> without weight, <hi>timber</hi> alſo and <hi>ſtone,</hi> charging <hi>Salomon</hi> to ariſe and be doing, and the <hi>Lord</hi> would be with him. He built this houſe of <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation</hi> for the Lord, a place for his <hi>dwelling</hi> for euer: 2. <hi>Chr.</hi> 6.2. but it was <hi>conditionall</hi> from God:<note place="margin">2. Chr. 6.2.</note> 
               <hi>If</hi> yee turne away and forſake my ſtatutes and my comman<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dements, this houſe which I haue ſanctified for my name, will l <hi>caſt</hi> out of my ſight, and will make it to be a Prouerbe and a <hi>by-word</hi> among all nations. And this houſe which is <hi>high,</hi> ſhall be an <hi>aſtoniſhment</hi> to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one that paſſeth by it: 2. <hi>Chr.</hi> 7. <hi>Nabucadnezzar</hi> King of <hi>Bayblon</hi> in the ninth yeare of his raigne,<note place="margin">2 Chr. 7.21.</note> beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged it: <hi>Nebuzardan</hi> Captaine of his Guarde, in the nineteenth yeere of his raigne, burnt this <hi>houſe</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> and the <hi>Kings houſe,</hi> and all the houſes of <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> and euery great mans houſe, with fire, 2. <hi>King.</hi> 25.<note place="margin">2 Kin. 25.9.</note> 
               <hi>So that there was little hope euer to ſee it reſtored againe:</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:986:5"/>yet <hi>Cyrus</hi> proclaimed the reedefying of it, reſtored the fiue thouſand and foure hundreth veſſels of <hi>golde</hi> and <hi>ſiluer,</hi> which <hi>Nabucadnezzar</hi> had put in the houſe of his gods,<note place="margin">Ezra. 1.11.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.7</note> and gaue a grant to bring <hi>Cedar trees</hi> from <hi>Lebanon</hi> to the ſea of <hi>Ioppa.</hi> Yet againe it was hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered till the ſecond yeare of <hi>Darius,</hi> who was ſo reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute for the building thereof, that he made this decree: <hi>Whoſoeuer ſhall alter this word, let timber be pulled downe from his houſe, and being ſet vp, let him be hanged there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and let his houſe be made a dung-hill for this:</hi> And the <hi>God</hi> that hath cauſed his name to dwell there, deſtroy all <hi>Kings</hi> and people, that ſhal put to their hand to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and to ceſtroy this houſe of <hi>God,</hi> which is at <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.</hi> I <hi>Darius</hi> haue made a decree, let it be done with ſpeed. <hi>Ezra.</hi> 6. It was finiſhed,<note place="margin">Ezra. 6.12</note> and afterward <hi>Iudas Macchabeus</hi> purged it from the prophanation of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> vpon the fiue and twentieth day of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth <hi>Caſleu</hi> anſwerable to our <hi>December;</hi> ordayning that the dedication ſhould be kept in its ſeaſon, from yeere to yeere with mirth and gladnes.<note place="margin">1. Macc. 4.59</note> A <hi>Ceremonie</hi> continuing til <hi>Chriſt,</hi> &amp; honored by his <hi>preſence</hi> in an <hi>annuall</hi> memoriall mentioned in theſe wordes. <hi>And it was at Ieruſalem, &amp;c.</hi> Great was the glory of <hi>Salomons</hi> Temple, the length wherof was 60. cubites, and the bredth 20. cubits, and the height 30 cubits, 1. <hi>King.</hi> 6.7. years in building, ouerlayd with pure <hi>gold,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 6.38, 21.</note> the altar &amp; tables wheron the Shew-bread was ſet were of <hi>gold,</hi> the candleſticks, flowers, lamps, tongs of perfect gold, the ſnuffers, baſons, ſpoons &amp; cenſers of pure <hi>gold,</hi> the entry of the houſe,<note place="margin">2 Chr. 4.22</note> and the doores of the houſe of the Temple, were of <hi>gold,</hi> 2. <hi>Chr.</hi> 4. inſomuch that many of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:986:6"/>the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Leuites,</hi> and chiefe of the Fathers who were ancient men, that had ſeen the firſt houſe, when the foundation of the ſecond was layd before theyr eyes,<note place="margin">Ez. 3, 12. Hagg. 2.9.</note> they wept with a loud voyce, <hi>Ez.</hi> 3. <hi>Haggai</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged them, The glory of this latter houſe ſhal be greater then the former,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ribera in Hag.</hi> 2 King 45.</note> 
               <hi>Hag.</hi> 2. which <hi>Ribera</hi> thinketh fulfilled in <hi>Herods</hi> reparations, when the gold ouerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued al the reſt, &amp; the ſtones were in length 25. cubits, in bredth 12. in height 8,<note place="margin">I <hi>ſephus l.</hi> 15. <hi>antiq. c.</hi> 14. Mat. 13. 1. Mar. 13, 1. <hi>Orig. Chryſ. Theoph.</hi>
               </note> which made the Diſciples ſhew <hi>Chriſt</hi> the buildings of the <hi>Temple,</hi> Mat. 24. and ſay, <hi>Maſter, ſee what maner of ſtones, and what buildings are here. Mar.</hi> 13. pittying that euer it <hi>ſhould,</hi> or thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it impoſſible that euer it <hi>might,</hi> be left deſolate as was threatned, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.38. but howſoeuer it was <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans</hi> policy, ſaith iuditious <hi>Caluin,</hi> by <hi>Herods</hi> impoſture to draw away the minds of men from adorning their ſpirituall Temples,<note place="margin">Calu in Agg. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> by looking vpon the ſuperfluous glory of that outward Temple:<note place="margin">Carthuſ. Abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenſis: Ioſ. l. <hi>8</hi> Ant c. <hi>3</hi> sic vocatur in hyſtoria Ethio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pica, quam cit it Gloſſa, <hi>1. King. 10.7.</hi> Vatablus. Dec. in. Agg. Au. l. <hi>18.</hi> ciu. c. <hi>45.</hi>
               </note> I cannot beleeue it came neere to <hi>Salomons</hi> for ſtate, which the <hi>Queene</hi> of <hi>Saba</hi> wondred at, <hi>Malceda</hi> which came to proue him with hard queſtions, &amp; concluded ſeeing his wiſdom, <hi>and the houſe that he had built:</hi> thy <hi>wiſdom</hi> and <hi>proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> exceedeth the fame which I heard: 1, <hi>Kin.</hi> 10. In an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other reſpect this <hi>Temple</hi> was more illuſtrious then <hi>Salomons, In Chriſts preſence</hi> in it, and miracles, as <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom</hi> and <hi>Auſten</hi> thinke. Now hee graced the Feaſt of the <hi>Dedication</hi> at <hi>Ieruſalem. And it was at Hieruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Text well befitting the occaſion of this Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> met to behold the <hi>Conſecrating and De<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dicating of a little Temple vnto God,</hi> warranting the bleſſing and ſanctifying of it, by the <hi>Prayers</hi> of a <hi>Reue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rend
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:986:6"/>Father</hi> of our Church. I will not follow the words in an <hi>Allegorie,</hi> that <hi>Chriſt</hi> being a <hi>new-Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuer,</hi> bringing a <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. a <hi>new Spirit,</hi> Ez. 36. <hi>A new co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor, 3 6, Ez. 36.26. Ioh. 13.34. Reu. 21, 1.</note> 
               <hi>Reu.</hi> 21. He would therfore come to a <hi>new Temple:</hi> to the <hi>Porch of Salomon</hi> in that Temple, becauſe as in <hi>Salomons</hi> time <hi>Peace</hi> was in <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ch 22.9.</note> 1. Chr. 22. ſo <hi>Chriſt</hi> came to make <hi>Peace</hi> betwixt heauen and earth In <hi>Winter</hi> becauſe their hearts were frozen, and loue <hi>cold,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bulling.</note> no life or ſpring of goodnes appearing amongſt the <hi>Iewes.</hi> I cannot handle the particulers as they offer themſelues, &amp; would be followed if the time out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran me not:<note place="margin">Aug. Bed. Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thym.</note> the place <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> the triumph at Ieruſalem in a <hi>Feaſt:</hi> the quality of the feaſt of the <hi>Dedication,</hi> the ſeaſon when it was ſolemnized, <hi>Winter,</hi> the Honourableſt perſonage of the Feaſt, though the Iews would haue ſtoned him, <hi>Ieſus,</hi> his abode there, for he <hi>walked:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ver. 31.</note> His publike walking in the <hi>Temple:</hi> His method in walking in that part, which was moſt fitte for him. In <hi>Salomons Porch,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I obſerue onely two circumſtances as the <hi>body</hi> and <hi>ſoule</hi> of theſe words.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The <hi>lawfulneſſe</hi> of Churches, their dedicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or conſecration, the remembrance whereof Chriſt abhorred not but frequented the <hi>annuall commemoration</hi> of a Temples Dedication, euen in Winter, <hi>And it was at Hieruſalem, the Feaſt of the Dedication, and it was Winter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 The <hi>honor</hi> of Chriſts preſentation of himſelfe eſpecially in <hi>Temples</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in <hi>Churches</hi> now. And <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:986:7"/>walked in the Temple in Salomons Porch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 1 is for <hi>building,</hi> repayring and dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of a <hi>Church,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond is, for the <hi>eſtabliſhing,</hi> continuing, and felicity of a <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt, we haue Gods <hi>houſe</hi> prepared in a place of <hi>vnity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſecond, we haue it <hi>frequented</hi> by the Author of Grace, and Peace, and <hi>Mercy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the 1. we haue <hi>Salomons</hi> temple beautified and <hi>re-edefied.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the 2. we haue a <hi>greater then Salomon</hi> in it, whereby it is exalted and <hi>honoured.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of which while I ſhall ſpeake, as my <hi>ſudden ſummons</hi> ſhall ſuffer me, ſcarſe hauing ſo many <hi>houres warning</hi> for this burthen, as there are words in my Text: Let me requeſt you all to remember that ſpeech of Sa nt <hi>Auguſtine: Qui in al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s habitat, humilibus appropinquat:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug.</note> He that dwelleth on high, diſcendeth down to the lowly: <hi>Deſcenae, vt aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das:</hi> Let vs with meekeneſſe affoorde our beſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, that we may aſcend to the true vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of this Text. Let vs caſt away all <hi>bitter cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures</hi> and by-thoughts, for the <hi>place</hi> whereon wee ſtand is holy ground. Let mee deſire you to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt me with your <hi>prayers,</hi> that what I ſpeake may bee to the <hi>glory</hi> of his name, and <hi>winning</hi> of ſoules vnto <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who for this cauſe, at the feaſt of the <hi>Dedication</hi> went vnto <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> as my firſt part leadeth me in order.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> was the holy City,<note place="margin">Ia.</note> 
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:986:7"/>
               <hi>Temple,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 4, 5.</note> a place which the Lord choſe that his name might bee there: <hi>Hee</hi> ſanctified it, that his eyes and heart might be there perpetually 2. <hi>Chr.</hi> 7. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> could not forget <hi>Hieruſalem Iſai</hi> badde her put on her beautifull garments:<note place="margin">2 Chr. 7.16.</note> 
               <hi>Iſa.</hi> 52.<note place="margin">Iſai. 52.1.</note> Promiſed that the ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nes of them that afflicted her, ſhould come bending vnto her; all they that deſpiſed her, ſhould bowe themſelues downe at the ſoles of her feet, and call her the City of the Lord, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 60.<note place="margin">Iſa. 60.14.</note> So did <hi>Zacharie,</hi> that the Lord of hoſtes would dwell in the midſt of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> ſhould be called a City of truth, and the <hi>Mountaine</hi> of the Lord of hoſtes: the <hi>holy mountaine, Zech.</hi> 8.<note place="margin">Zech. 8.3.</note> In <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> the <hi>Prophets</hi> preached, there it was fit that the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> ſhould beginne to preach repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and remiſſion of ſinnes, <hi>Luc.</hi> 24.<note place="margin">Luc. 24.47.</note> So it was foretold that the <hi>Word</hi> of the Lord ſhould goe forth from Ieruſalem,<note place="margin">Iſa. 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>Iſai.</hi> 2. <hi>Chriſt</hi> was promiſed to be ſent to the Iewes to be borne of <hi>Dauid,</hi> Pſal. 89. ver. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>32. of <hi>Abraham,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 89, 4. Pſal. 132.11 Gen. 22, 18. Gal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.16. <hi>Amb. l</hi> 1. <hi>de A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ac</hi> 18.</note> Gen. 22. as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> expoundeth that place, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Chriſt</hi> was there crucified, dead, buried, and thence he <hi>aſcended.</hi> His <hi>vertue</hi> was to bee diffuſed throughout the whole world, and therefore in the <hi>midſt</hi> and <hi>nauill</hi> of the habitable world, hee ſhewed himſelfe moſt conſpicuouſly. It was fitte for his humility as to ſuffer the <hi>ſhamefulleſt</hi> death,<note place="margin">In medio terrae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atus eſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Pſal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>3,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> ſo not to be aſhamed of the moſt <hi>eminent</hi> place: He tooke vpon him the <hi>forme</hi> of a ſeruant, and therefore as he choſe <hi>Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lehem</hi> for his birth, ſo hee choſe <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> for his paſſion. He that would not ſuffer a <hi>Prophet</hi> to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:986:8"/>out of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> c. 13.33. would ſuffer there himſelfe, being the <hi>Prince</hi> of Prophets. He char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> not to depart from <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act 1.4, <hi>Chryſ.</hi>
               </note> but waite for the promiſe of the Father, <hi>Act.</hi> 1. <hi>confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming</hi> them leſt they ſhould faint liuing amongſt the <hi>crucifiers</hi> of their Lord, or <hi>faſtning</hi> them there a while, leaſt departing thence ſuddenly, others might haue thought they had deſpayred of their Lords <hi>reſurrection.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Oecumen. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt Ant. l. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> Some call it <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> becauſe <hi>Dauid</hi> compaſſed it with a wall. <hi>Maſius,</hi> becauſe the Lord eſpecially looked towards it.<note place="margin">Ierch. Salem. Salem: Alta.</note> 
               <hi>Salmecon,</hi> becauſe it was exceeding high, <hi>Euſebius</hi> of <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> Temple. <hi>Sydonius Apollinaris</hi> noteth that when it is read <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Others of</hi> Raah <hi>&amp;</hi> Salem. Viſio Pacis.</note> it may ſignifie Heauen: but when <hi>Ieroſolymae,</hi> it muſt be taken for an earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Citie. <hi>Beza</hi> reades it heere, <hi>Hieroſolymis:</hi> It was <hi>famous</hi> for <hi>Herods</hi> Hall, the Sepulchres of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid, Steuen, Nichodemus, Gamaliel, Zacharie, Mount Syon, Mount Oliuet,</hi> the brooke <hi>Cedron, Ieremyes caue, the Virgins houſe:</hi> but more famous for <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> Temple, which being repayred was ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized with a dedication. Famous for</p>
            <p>The many names of it mentioned by <hi>Toſtatus-Solyma,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>In Mat.</hi> 4, q, 32,</note> 
               <hi>Luza, Bethel, Ieroſolyma, Iebus, Elia, Vrbs ſacra, Ieruſalem dicitur, atque Salem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Famous</hi> for the ſafety of it, which was ſecure, as <hi>Dauid</hi> told old <hi>Barzillai:</hi> Come thou ouer with me, and I will feede thee with mee in <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 19, 33,</note> 2. Sam. 19. yet all theſe and the aboundance of <hi>wealth,</hi> ſiluer being there as ſtones, and <hi>Cedars</hi> as the <hi>Sycomore</hi> trees that are in the vale for aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:986:8"/>1. <hi>King,</hi> 10. made it not ſo famous as the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and the Feaſts:<note place="margin">1. King. 10.27</note> the Iewes had a <hi>Feaſt</hi> of the <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath,</hi> the <hi>Paſſeouer,</hi> firſt <hi>Fruites,</hi> of <hi>Pentecoſt,</hi> of <hi>Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets,</hi> of <hi>Attonement,</hi> of <hi>Tabernacles,</hi> Leu. 23.<note place="margin">Leu. 23.</note> 
               <hi>Salomon</hi> had his feaſt of <hi>Dedication</hi> of the Temple, and all <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> with him, a great Congregation, from the entring in of <hi>Hamath,</hi> vnto the riuer of <hi>Egypt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. King. 8.65</note> ſeuen daies and ſeuen dayes, euen foureteene dayes, 1. <hi>King.</hi> 8. So hath our Church <hi>ſolemne Feaſtes, in ſtead</hi> of the <hi>Paſſeouer,</hi> which was inſtituted in remembrance of the deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from <hi>Egypts</hi> bondage; of <hi>pentecoſt,</hi> a remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the <hi>Law</hi> giuen at Mount <hi>Sinai;</hi> of the <hi>Feaſt</hi> of <hi>Tabernacles,</hi> a remembrance of <hi>Iſraels</hi> dwelling in <hi>Tents,</hi> forty yeares in the wilderneſſe: Wee haue <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> in honour of Chriſts <hi>Incarnation;</hi> which <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> calleth the <hi>Metropolis</hi> of all other Feaſts:<note place="margin">Chryſ.</note> 
               <hi>Eaſter</hi> in honour of Chriſts <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> which <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> calleth the <hi>Kings</hi> day, and the <hi>eminentſt of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; Leo</hi> the <hi>Feaſt of feaſts; Nazianzen</hi> holds it as farre excelling the reſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leo.</hi> 1.</note> as the Sunne doth other Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets; <hi>Whitſontide,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertul. l: de Corona militis. Orig. l. <hi>8.</hi> contra Celſum. <hi>Act. 20.16. Queſtion.</hi>
               </note> in honour of Chriſts confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> by ſending vnto vs the <hi>Holy Ghoſt;</hi> a <hi>Feaſt</hi> which cauſed <hi>Paul</hi> to haſten his iourney towards <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> Act. 20. So that if any queſtion it,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why doth one day excell another, when as all the light of euery day in the yeere is of the ſunne?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It may be anſwered:<note place="margin">Anſwere.</note> By the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of the Lord they were diſtinguiſhed, and he altered <hi>ſeaſons</hi> and Feaſts: Some of them hath hee made <hi>High dayes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 33, 8.</note> &amp; hallowed them, and ſome of them hath he made <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary dayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:986:9"/>Would wee know the <hi>Authors</hi> of Feaſts to <hi>Iewes</hi> or <hi>Chriſtians:</hi> By the commandement of <hi>God himſelf</hi> in the mouth of <hi>Moſes</hi> thoſe were ordained, <hi>Leu.</hi> 23. and ſome others called <hi>Regular, Ordinary</hi> and <hi>vſuall: Or</hi> by the <hi>Will</hi> of the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> vpon ſome reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble cauſe; yet no part of <hi>Will-worſhip,</hi> being not <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Legem Dei, againſt the Law of God;</hi> but <hi>ſecundum analogiam Legis, according to the analogie of the Law,</hi> as this <hi>feaſt</hi> of Dedication, that <hi>feaſt</hi> of the 14. and 15. of the moneth <hi>Adar,</hi> Eſt: 9.21. and ſome others. The <hi>Iewes</hi> not onely added to the number of the Feaſtes inſtituted by <hi>Moſes,</hi> but augmented the <hi>ſolemnity</hi> of thoſe feaſts which <hi>Moſes</hi> appointed: For whereas <hi>Dies Calendarum,</hi> or <hi>Neomeniae</hi> the firſt day of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, or Feaſt of <hi>New Moones</hi> was appointed onelie for ſacrifice to God, and not mentioned amongſt thoſe ſolemne feſtiuities, yet the Iewes appointed for the encreaſe of the ſeruice of God, that not onely ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices ſhould bee offered in them, but alſo men ſhould abſtaine from all ſeruile labour, and ſo make it an Holy-day, and great ſolemnity. Thus was it in <hi>Dauids</hi> time: <hi>Blow vp the Trumpet in the new Moone,</hi> in the time appointed on our ſolemn feaſt day: <hi>Pſ.</hi> 81. It was <hi>celebrious</hi> for the benefite of gouernment;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal. 81.3.</hi> Nye, de Lyra.</note> for in the <hi>New-Moone</hi> there appeared the change of time: and therefore was it ſo vſed in <hi>Eliſhaes</hi> time, to whom when the <hi>Shunamite</hi> woman deſired to goe for her dead child; her husband ſayd, Wherfore wilt thou go to him to day: It is neyther <hi>New-Moone,</hi> nor <hi>Sabbath,</hi> 2. King. 4.<note place="margin">2. King. 4.23.</note> Which argueth, that they were freed from labour, becauſe her husband inſinuated, that ſhee
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:986:9"/>ſhould goe vpon a day when hee might bee at leaſure from his buſineſſe, making in that reſpect a ſimilitude betwixt the <hi>Calends</hi> and the <hi>Sabbath:</hi> and in S. <hi>Aug:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. l. de <hi>10</hi> Apocd. <hi>15</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> time, reprouing the Iewiſh woman, holding that they were better to <hi>ſpinne,</hi> or doe any worke then immodeſtly daunce in theyr New <hi>Moons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the Feaſts of Chriſtians, <hi>Chriſt</hi> inſtituted no Holy-dayes in his <hi>life</hi> time, he abrogated not the law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> but obſerued thoſe Feaſts: Neyther did the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> till the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> beeing dead, it might be buried honorably. It was not fit that <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion ſhould haue ſo many ceremonies or Holy-daies in the Cradle, as it had in the full age of it. Yet in the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> time, the <hi>Lords day,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 1, 10. Act. 20, 7. 1. Cor. 16, 2. Mar. 16.2. <hi>Oecumen. Anſelm. Primaſ,</hi>
               </note> Apoc. 1. our <hi>Sunday</hi> was inſtituted by the Apoſtles in remembrance of the Reſurrection of our Sauiour: For the Sabbath is ceremoniall for the manner, though morall for the matter. The <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of it is <hi>de iure diuino,</hi> though ſome ceremonies of it, <hi>de iure humano.</hi> The <hi>Iewes</hi> ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated theyr Sabbath the ſeuenth day, Wee the eight: They gaue God the laſt day of the Weeke:<note place="margin">Philo. l de opificio Mundi.</note> wee the firſt: They kept theyr Sabbath in honour of the Worlds <hi>creation:</hi> but wee ours in memoriall of the worlds <hi>Redemption,</hi> a worke of greater might and mercie. The <hi>Moſt of our great feſtiuities,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug ad Lanuar. Clem: l. <hi>5,</hi> c. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> S. <hi>Auſten</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribeth it to the authoritie of the Apoſtles, or general Councels, as the Feaſts of <hi>Chriſts Natiuity, Circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Paſsion, Reſurrection, Aſcenſion, ſending of the holy Ghoſt, and ſome beſides theſe,</hi> kept vpon ſet dayes eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry yeare:<note place="margin">Aug:</note> 
               <hi>Ne volumine temporum ingrata ſubrepat obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uio</hi> (ſayth hee) leſt in ſucceſſe of time, vnthankefull
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:986:10"/>forgetfulneſſe creepe in by little and little, and cauſe ſuch things to be forgotten which the <hi>Righteous</hi> haue done, who ſhould bee in euerlaſting remembrance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men.</p>
            <p>Hence is it, that the <hi>Church</hi> keepeth thoſe <hi>Holy dayes,</hi> which <hi>Antiquity</hi> hath preſcribed, that all things bee done decently and in <hi>order,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.40.</note> 1. Cor. 14.40. But what <hi>order</hi> would there be, if euery man ſhould ſerue God at <hi>his owne pleaſure,</hi> at <hi>his owne time,</hi> after his <hi>owne manner?</hi> Wee retaine the Feſtiuals of <hi>Saints,</hi> becauſe wee deſire to <hi>prayſe</hi> God in his Saints,<note place="margin">Pſal. 150.1</note> for his great gifts and vertues beſtowed vpon them; being as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queathed <hi>Legacies,</hi> and onely true <hi>Reliques</hi> for vs, that wee may follow their good examples. Theſe <hi>dayes</hi> are for the ſeruice of God, and partly, as <hi>Socrates</hi> ſpake of olde <hi>(Quò ſe à laborum contentione relaxent)</hi> for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laxation from labour.<note place="margin">Socrat. l <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>21</hi>
               </note> Theſe wee keepe <hi>holy</hi> as the Lords day, <hi>in the ſame manner,</hi> though <hi>not in the ſame degree;</hi> not for <hi>worſhip</hi> to them, or imploring of them, but to <hi>worſhip</hi> the God of <hi>Martyrs</hi> and <hi>Saints;</hi> abſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from lawfull labour in them, not for <hi>ſuperſtition,</hi> in conſcience to the day, but <hi>obedience</hi> to the Church: And <hi>if it be held contemptuous to ſpend that day in law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full labour, wherein the Church ſhall indict a ſolemne faſt, notwithſtanding that liberty of the ſixe dayes which God hath giuen: why ſhall that bee lawfull in a caſe of deiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which may not in prayſe and exultation?</hi> If the Church had power to appoint a <hi>feſtiuall</hi> for the dedication of the Temple and the like, then it hath power to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the memoriall of the bleſſed <hi>Apoſtles.</hi> We ſee the <hi>Iewes</hi> did keepe the feaſt of the Dedication, which
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:986:10"/>was threefold as <hi>Alcuinus</hi> noteth: The firſt by <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> in the time of <hi>Autumne:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aleuinus.</note> The ſecond by <hi>Zoroba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel,</hi> in the time of the <hi>Spring:</hi> The third by <hi>Iudas Mac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chabaeus</hi> in <hi>Winter,</hi> the remembrance whereof conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued vntill Chriſts time.<note place="margin">The Grecians call to dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate or initiate, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but to conſecrate, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> To <hi>dedicate</hi> is one thing, to <hi>conſecrate</hi> is another: Things are ſayde to bee <hi>conſecrated,</hi> when of prophane things they are ſayde to bee religious and holy: and to bee <hi>dedicated,</hi> when they are appointed to God. The <hi>Hebrewes</hi> did not onely dedicate Temples which were newly built, but alſo thoſe which were repayred and clenſed from vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe: as <hi>Iudas Macchabaeus</hi> did the Temple here, when it was polluted by the <hi>Ethniques,</hi> with the moſt filthy Idolatry of <hi>Antiochus.</hi> Which Feaſts they called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Renoualia,</hi> or <hi>Renouales dies,</hi> dayes of renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; which are not once celebrated, but the ſolemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of them are done euery yeare once, as now when Chriſt came to the feaſt of the Dedication; whence I inferre this doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the conſecrating of Churches to the right ſeruice of the true God is a warrantable ceremonie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Doct.</note> 
               <hi>allowable by our Sauiours preſence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Reaſon</hi> of this thing may be drawne from that rule of the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 4 4.5.</note> 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4. <hi>Euery creature of God is good, and nothing to bee refuſed, if it bee receyued with thankſgiuing:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pet. Mart. <hi>4.4.</hi> of common place, pag: <hi>66.</hi>
               </note> For it is ſanctified by the Word of God and Prayer: It is meete that wee ſhould giue <hi>thankes</hi> vnto God, who hath giuen a place vnto his people, wherein they may meete together for the practiſe of holie things; and that wee ſhould pray for a right and perfect vſe of ſuch a place, that <hi>God</hi> there may bee
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:986:11"/>glorified, <hi>ſinnes</hi> confeſſed, holy <hi>doctrine</hi> adminiſtred, zealous <hi>Prayers</hi> frequented, a right <hi>diſcipline</hi> exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and <hi>almes</hi> cheerefully diſtributed. Was it not a <hi>Lawe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 20.5.</note> 
               <hi>Deut.</hi> 20 that an Officer ſhould ſpeake vnto the people in battell? What man is there that hath built a new houſe, and hath not dedicated it? Let him goe and returne to his houſe, leſt hee dye in the battell and another man dedicate it: <hi>and ſhall not Gods houſe bee dedicated?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 20,</note> Thus <hi>Dauid</hi> did dedicate his houſe, and intitled the thirtieth Pſalme, <hi>Schic Channucath Beth Le Dauid: A ſong at the Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the houſe of Dauid.</hi> And <hi>Salomon</hi> his ſonne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated Gods houſe, At the <hi>dedication</hi> of the wall of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> the <hi>Leuites</hi> were ſought out of their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to keepe the dedication with gladnes, with thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing, and with ſinging, with <hi>Cymbals, Pſalteries</hi> &amp; with <hi>Harpes;</hi> and the ſonnes of the Singers gathered themſelues together, both out of the plaine Country round about <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> and from the villages of <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophathi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Neh. 12.28.</hi> Euſeb. l. <hi>9.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi> biſt: Eccleſ. &amp; l. <hi>4.</hi> de vita Conſt Magni.</note> 
               <hi>Neh.</hi> 12. Thus <hi>Conſtantine</hi> when he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payred <hi>Bizantium,</hi> and determined to vſe that City for the ſeat of the <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> deſired to dedicate it to God, and to that end called 318: Fathers which then held the Synode of <hi>Nice.</hi> This great <hi>Emperour</hi> went to <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> and built a Temple, dedicating vnto God the ſame by <hi>Biſhoppes,</hi> which held a Councell at <hi>Tyrus. Gregory Nazianzene</hi> giueth a reaſon, why Churches were dedicated,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Greg: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> de vſu Eccl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſiae</hi> Pſal. 51, 10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 4.24. Col. 3.10.</note> to remember the hearers of renuing themſelues by a right Spirit, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. To put on the new man, <hi>Ep.</hi> 4. which is renewed in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, <hi>Col.</hi> 3. For there is no holineſſe in outwarde
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:986:11"/>things, they are not capable of diuine qualities, but beeing conſecrate doe become inſtruments of the Spirit, whereby our Faith is ſtirred vp. The <hi>Lord</hi> by his Word commaundeth the faithfull to vſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayers,<note place="margin">Calu. Inſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>: l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>20,</hi> ſ. <hi>30.</hi>
               </note> and for this purpoſe there muſt bee common Temples, ſo that men refuſing to <hi>commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate</hi> theyr prayers with the people of God, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into their chambers, breake the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God. Theſe common <hi>Temples</hi> muſt bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated by common prayers: For if Saint <hi>Paul</hi> would not vndertake his <hi>iourney</hi> without Prayer,<note place="margin">Act. 20.36.</note> 
               <hi>Act.</hi> 20. If <hi>Dauid</hi> dedicated the <hi>morning</hi> vnto God by prayer, Pſal. 143. and the <hi>Euening</hi> by Prayer,<note place="margin">Pſal 143.8. Pſal, 77.6. Pſal. 71.18. Pſal. 141.2. <hi>Soz. l.</hi> 4, <hi>c.</hi> 13.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 77. &amp; his <hi>olde age</hi> by prayer: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 71. and his <hi>prayers</hi> by a pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 141. Why ſhould not the <hi>houſe</hi> of Prayer bee dedicated vnto God by Prayer? By Prayer <hi>Baſil</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated a Temple which hee had newly built, calling vnto him his Neighbour Biſhopps.<note place="margin">Clem. Ep. ad Licobum.</note> So <hi>Clemens</hi> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained; Make Churches in fit places and let them be ſanctified by Prayer. So <hi>Athanaſius</hi> confeſſed of the <hi>African</hi> Churches, that they were thus dedicated.<note place="margin">Athan: in Apo, ad Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantin. Lau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ius to. <hi>1.</hi> de vitis Sanctorum.</note> So practiſed <hi>Auxibius</hi> a Scholler of Saint <hi>Maries,</hi> and an Archbiſhop, if wee beleeue <hi>Metaphraſtes:</hi> He came into a Church newly built, fell downe, wept and prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: <hi>Lord God,</hi> which madeſt heauen and earth, the Sea and all that therein is: <hi>Strengthen</hi> me thy ſeruant: giue me boldneſſe that I may preach thy word freely, and without feare: Illuminate theſe preſent with thy grace, that being conuerted from the error of Sathan, they may acknowledge thee to be the true God, and whom thou haſt ſent Ieſus Chriſt. Mercifull God,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:986:12"/>let thy holy Spirit dwell in this holy houſe, which is built in thy holy name; confirme and eſtabliſh it, keepe it immoueable in thy faith, euen vnto the end of the world. This was the forme of Dedication then; and that <hi>Salomons</hi> conſiſted of a Prayer,<note place="margin">1. King. 8.22.23.</note> wee finde, 1. <hi>King.</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 1. Which being ſo, it may direct vs to auoyd the errors of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in her dedications, holding from the 2. <hi>Councell of Braca,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Conc:</hi> 2. <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n:</hi> 5.</note> that a Church ſhould not be conſecrated till prouiſion be made for gifts and reuenues, and that there ſhould ſtill be <hi>lights</hi> in the Church; the firſt part whereof is conuenient, but the ſecond needleſſe: what vſe is there of <hi>lightes,</hi> vnleſſe men meete earely in the mornings, as thoſe Chriſtians were conſtrained to doe in <hi>Plinies</hi> time;<note place="margin">Can. de conſcer. Diſt: <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> or late in the darke <hi>euenings? holding,</hi> that <hi>Temples</hi> ſhould not be built or conſecrated,<note place="margin">Con. of Wormes, c. <hi>3.</hi> &amp; in c. Miſſarum ſolennia. Tribis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enſis Synod: Ann. <hi>812</hi>
               </note> but by the will of the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> which is a palpable <hi>tyranny</hi> and vſurped authority: <hi>holding,</hi> that ſeruice muſt not bee ſayd or ſung, but in places ſo dedicated; whereas in caſe of <hi>neceſſity</hi> it may bee otherwiſe, and deuotions may bee performed ſomtimes in other places; as <hi>Izhak</hi> pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the field, <hi>Iſrael</hi> in <hi>Egypt, Moſes</hi> at the Sea, <hi>Elias</hi> vnder a tree, <hi>Ieremie</hi> in a dungeon, <hi>Ionas</hi> in the belly of the Whale, <hi>Chriſt</hi> vpon the toppe of a mountain, the <hi>Diſciples</hi> in a ſhippe: <hi>holding</hi> that all things muſt be done now in the dedicating of the <hi>Temples</hi> of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, which were done in dedicating the Temples of the <hi>Iewes;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gratian, diſt. <hi>1.</hi> de Conſecr.</note> whereas howſoeuer in <hi>morall</hi> duties we are more bound then they were, yet not in <hi>ceremonies,</hi> figures, ſhadowes, ſeeing the commaundements of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:986:12"/>that kind were aboliſhed by the death of <hi>Chriſt: Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> that the dedicating of Churches driueth thence Diuels,<note place="margin">Cont. Col: Anno <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>36</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> whereas <hi>Romaniſts</hi> cannot challenge this po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to driue away Sathan at their pleaſure: For the <hi>Spirit</hi> diuideth ſeuerally to euery man, as hee will: 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. They know not whether any bad <hi>Spirits</hi> bee there,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 11.</note> though ſometimes it appeareth that in ſome wicked places euill Spirites haue haunted and inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted;<note place="margin">Pln. <hi>2</hi> l. <hi>7.</hi> Epiſt.</note> as by their effects hath appeared, which hath cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed none willingly there to inhabite: they may as well <hi>coniure</hi> the whole world, ſeeing Saint <hi>Paul</hi> calleth the <hi>Diuels,</hi> the Rulers of the darkeneſſe of this World, Ep. 6. <hi>Yea often it is knowne, that worſe Spirits can not frequent thoſe places then themſelues.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epi.</hi> 6.13.</note> Their other <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies</hi> are ridiculous, of twelue <hi>Candles</hi> before twelue <hi>Images,</hi> ſignifying the twelue <hi>Apoſtles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſpin: de Orig: dedicat:</note> and that we muſt walke in light: of three times <hi>walking</hi> round, ſignifying <hi>Chriſts</hi> triple circuite (more then he made) from <hi>heauen</hi> to the world; from the <hi>world</hi> to <hi>Limbus;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Io: Sleid: l. <hi>21.</hi> Commenta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> from <hi>Limbus</hi> to heauen: or the threefold eſtate of the <hi>Church;</hi> of <hi>married,</hi> of <hi>widdowes,</hi> of <hi>Virgins:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dura: in Rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onali Diu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> l. <hi>1:</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> of three times <hi>knocking</hi> at the doore, ſignifying the three-fold right which <hi>God</hi> hath in our hearts, becauſe he made vs, redeemed vs, and hath giuen himſelfe vnto vs: of <hi>ſprinckling</hi> water, ſignifying <hi>Baptiſme</hi> and <hi>Repentance:</hi> of making <hi>characters</hi> in aſhes caſt vpon the pauement, with lines drawne from the right hand vnto the left, and from the left hand vnto the right, ſignifying the coniunction of two people: Their aſcribing <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons</hi> at ſuch times of Dedication, are as vaine;<note place="margin">Anns Dom. <hi>1066.</hi>
               </note> as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> the ſecond gaue vnto any one that came de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoutly
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:986:13"/>to the dedication at <hi>Caſſina,</hi> 40, dayes remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:<note place="margin">G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eg. Nicae: Synod<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>2.</hi> Anno <hi>788.</hi>
               </note> their burning of <hi>incenſe</hi> in them; their bringing of <hi>reliques</hi> to ſuch dedications; their inuocating of the <hi>Martyrs,</hi> to whom they build Churches. Wee ſtand for a <hi>Dedication</hi> by prayer of ſuch places, but caſt away thoſe gulleries.<note place="margin">Aug. de Ciu l. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>27.</hi>
               </note> The <hi>Gentiles</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auſtin</hi>) erected tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to their Gods: ſo did our <hi>Brittaines</hi> ſometimes in <hi>Scotland,</hi> a Temple to <hi>Mars;</hi> in <hi>Cornewall</hi> a Temple to <hi>Mercurie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Stow: Ann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. Cambd: Brittan. B. Iewel. Tract: de Sacris Scriptu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. pag. <hi>129.</hi>
               </note> in <hi>Bangor</hi> a temple to <hi>Minerua,</hi> in <hi>Eſſex</hi> a temple to <hi>Victoria,</hi> in <hi>Leyceſter</hi> a temple to <hi>Ianus;</hi> in <hi>Yorke</hi> where <hi>Peters</hi> is now, a temple to <hi>Bellona;</hi> in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> where <hi>Paul</hi> is now, a temple to <hi>Diana:</hi> No more then three and fifty yeares before the Incarnation of Chriſt (when <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> came out of <hi>France</hi> into <hi>England</hi>) ſo abſurd were our people to ſerue theſe falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuppoſed Gods and Goddeſſes: but now the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell being preached, theſe are baniſhed, &amp; ſuch dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe diſpelled. Our Churches and Chappels are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated to the true God; the very name <hi>Kirke,</hi> or Church, an abbreuiation of (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) the Lords houſe, ſounding ſo much.<note place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n l. <hi>4</hi> c. <hi>16</hi>
               </note> Wee ſay as <hi>Damaſcene,</hi> We build Temples vnto God in the names of the Saints; as <hi>Aug:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. l <hi>8.</hi> de Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit. Dei c. vlt. &amp; l. <hi>22.</hi> de Ciu. c. <hi>10</hi>
               </note> We build not temples vnto our Martyrs as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Gods, but memorials as vnto dead men, whoſe Spirits with God are ſtill liuing. Wee doe not crye at the Altars, O <hi>Peter! O Paul!</hi> O <hi>Cyprian!</hi> wee offer vnto thee our oblation; but at theyr <hi>Memorials,</hi> we offer to God, who made them men and <hi>Martyrs,</hi> giuing thanks for theyr victories, and encouraging our ſelues by calling vpon God, to the like Crowns of <hi>Martyrdome.</hi> If we retaine the names of ſome, who
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:986:13"/>were not <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> by calling Churches after theyr names, we doe but as Saint <hi>Luke,</hi> who vſed the name of <hi>Mars</hi> hill, where the <hi>Areopagites</hi> ſate, Act.<note place="margin">Act. 17.19.22 Act 28.11.</note> 17: and the names of <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux</hi> falſe Gods, Act. 28: and <hi>Iob</hi> and <hi>Amos</hi> the names of <hi>Arcturus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 9.9.38.31 Amos 5.8.</note> 
               <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion, Pleiades,</hi> Iob. 9, notwithſtanding, they had fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulous and poeticall fictions. The moſt of our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches haue the names of <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Martyrs,</hi> which we vſe, as they doe alſo in <hi>Geneua (that miraculous Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie for many diſtreſſed Proteſtants)</hi> their chiefe church retayning the name of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> another of Saint <hi>Magdalen,</hi> another of Saint <hi>Geruaſe,</hi> whither they vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally reſort to holy exerciſes.</p>
            <p>If any of our <hi>Churches</hi> were erected by the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious, wee muſt acknowledge how much wee are bound to God, that wee may haue ſuch houſes which we builded not; wels which wee digged not; <hi>Deut.</hi> 6: enioy thoſe Churches which wee prepared not,<note place="margin">Deu. 6.11.</note> as <hi>Noah</hi> had the benefit of that Arke, which was framed by ſome prophane Ship-wright:<note place="margin">Ludolphus.</note> Our <hi>Churches</hi> haue the pure Goſpell, the true Sacraments, and are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated vnto God by prayer; which we defend as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing our Sauiour, who will haue his houſe to bee called a houſe of Prayer, being preſent at the Feaſt of the dedication of it in <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">VSE. 2.</note>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 2. Which may ſerue for an <hi>Inſtruction</hi> to vs, to bee carefull for the dedicating of our Temples vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, both <hi>Materiall</hi> and <hi>Spirituall.</hi>
               <note place="margin">A Materiall Temple.</note> Our <hi>Materiall</hi> Temples are Houſes of wood and ſtone prepared for the aſſemblies of Chriſtians: yet Few vſe them as dedicated vnto God. <hi>Popiſh Recuſants</hi> are out of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:986:14"/>loue with our dedicated houſes becau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>erein their Maſſe-Prieſts and vnknowne languag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is ſilenced, their Images defaced, their idolatrous inuocations &amp; adorations abandoned; and would haue their refrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie fancie to be called by the name of Conſcience: they are inuited here to the Supper of the Lambe, yet will not come; and therefore well by the Magiſtrate may be compelled to come in,<note place="margin">Luc. 14.23.</note> that the houſe may be full. A bleſſed compulſion it is for a man to be dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to truth, for a woman to bee forced to heauen. The <hi>idle Libertine</hi> preferreth his Couch before our dedicated Temples,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amban Pſal.</hi> 129. Iſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 29.13.</note> herein worſe then the Iew, who did yeeld his ſpeech and preſence to the word; but he (forſooth) will not come ſo farre as the Church, though he be very neare it: or if ſuch come, we may ſay as <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> of ſome in his time; We ſee them ſtand and trifle while <hi>Prayer</hi> is ſayde;<note place="margin">Chryſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>om. <hi>24</hi> in Acta.</note> yea, not onely when <hi>Prayer</hi> is ſayde, but when the Prieſt bleſſeth. <hi>Doe you not know that you ſtand with the Angels, ſing and ſay Hymnes with them, &amp; ſtand you laughing?</hi> It were no maruel, if God ſhould ſend out a <hi>thunderbolt</hi> not only vpon them,<note place="margin">Hom, <hi>36.</hi> in <hi>1.</hi> ad Cor.</note> but vpon vs alſo: for ſurely theſe thinges deſerue a thunderbolt. The Church is not a <hi>Barbars ſhoppe,</hi> or an <hi>Apothecaries houſe,</hi> or a common court; but a place of <hi>Angels,</hi> the Court of <hi>Heauen,</hi> and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen it ſelfe.<note place="margin">Chryſ. <hi>15,</hi> in Heb.</note> Were they to enter into a <hi>Princes</hi> court, they would order their habite, looke and gate; but entring into the Church, the Court of the heauenly King, they laugh, iangle, walke, and make bargaines. It is Gods <hi>houſe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. Regula.</note> Let nothing bee done heere, but what may be fit for the preſence of God; the name
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:986:14"/>of it teacheth vs to pray: It is houſe of <hi>Prayer. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence</hi> is due to the very Cloyſters &amp; Churchyards; the bodyes of many Saints lodging there in peace, whoſe ſoules reſt with God in Heauen. The <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſt</hi> or <hi>Donatiſt</hi> (an old <hi>Rogatian</hi>) is ſo peeuiſh, that hee abſtaineth from the aſſemblies of all other men whatſoeuer, not of his opinion; and vpon conceit of ſome ſpots in our dedicated Churches, ſingles him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with his ſchiſmatical troupe to ſom odde corner, in a priuate houſe, wood, or barne in the night and darkeneſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> louing darkeneſſe, and therefore walking in darkeneſſe: or thinking their priuate conuenticle to be the onely true Church, becauſe they conceiue ſome <hi>ſpots,</hi> and ſpotted men doe remayne amongſt vs, not lamenting, praying, labouring for a redreſſe; but auoyding the land, which is no <hi>true valour</hi> to run away; eſpecially to <hi>places</hi> which are common <hi>harbours</hi> of all opinions and hereſies, where they cannot but draw in ſome <hi>ſtench</hi> of theſe; hauing left the free and cleare aire of the Goſpel, ſwallowing in <hi>Camels</hi> there, who could not endure <hi>Gnats</hi> here. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> tooke another courſe, <hi>For the chaffes ſake wee doe not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the threſhing-floore of the Lord;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. Ep. <hi>48.</hi>
               </note> nor for the bad fiſhes doe we breake the net of the Lord; nor for the <hi>Goates</hi> which are to be ſeuered in the end, do we leaue the Flocke of the Lord; nor for the veſſels made to diſhonour, doe wee flit out of the houſe of the Lord. <hi>Let</hi> vs reſolue ſo, to pray for any thing that may ſeem to be amiſſe, knowing that the Spouſe will be blacke, while ſhe is vpon earth, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1:<note place="margin">Can. 1.5.</note> that in the beſt field where Chriſt ſowed ſeede, and the beſt ſeede, tares
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:986:15"/>ſpring vp as well as wheate, and both muſt grow to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether till the Harueſt,<note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.30.</note> 
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. <hi>Let</hi> vs not flie from theſe materiall dedicated Temples, but hold it our ioy, that here wee may come to dedicate and deuote our ſelues vnto God. <hi>Wee our ſelues are ſpirituall Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.17. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pirituall Temple.</note> Our ſoules are the Temples of God: If any man defile the Temple of God, him ſhall God deſtroy; for the Temple of <hi>God</hi> is holy, which Temple yee are. Our bodies in compariſon of our ſoules, are but as wals of clay, encompaſſing a treaſure; as the woodden boxes of pretious <hi>Iewels;</hi> a courſe caſe to a ſweete in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, or a maske to a beautifull face: It is holie, we muſt not prophane it: God created it in infuſion, and infuſed it in creation. It ſhould bee holy as he is holy: without <hi>holineſſe</hi> wee can neyther bee named, nor be Chriſtians. It is the <hi>Riches</hi> of the <hi>Saints,</hi> the beauty of <hi>Angeis,</hi> delight of <hi>God.</hi> Whoſoeuer hath this, is a Temple of God; and he that wanteth it is a dwelling place of Sathan. <hi>Let</hi> the ſoule be free from ſinne,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and Sathan will bee driuen farre from the ſoule of the finner, and he ſhall dedicate this Temple vnto God.<note place="margin">A celeſtiall Temple.</note> There is another <hi>Temple,</hi> and it is celeſtiall, which if wee deſire to feaſt in, we muſt bee dedicated in bodies and ſoules vnto God; we muſt glorifie God here, and then wee ſhall bee glorified by him there: <hi>Bleſſed</hi> are al they that dwel in this houſe, they ſhall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be prayſing of God;<note place="margin">Pſal. 64.4.</note> there <hi>Charitie</hi> ſhall bee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>umb l.</hi> 4. <hi>l.</hi> 49.</note> Euery man ſhall reioyce as much for anothers good as he doth for his owne: they that looked down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward here at ſorrow not to be repented of, ſhall there looke vpward at ioy: they that walked here in <hi>redde,</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:986:15"/>ſhall there be <hi>cloathed</hi> with white. Thinke that thou one day mayeſt come into this Temple, as thou doeſt now into a material Temple.<note place="margin">Per <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Eccleſia intra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Paradiſi.</note> 
               <hi>This is the gate</hi> by which we muſt enter in. <hi>Here</hi> we muſt bee poliſhed as cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſtones for the heauenly Citie of <hi>Ieruſalem. Heere</hi> we fitte our ſelues with wedding garments, that wee be not caſt out into that place, where is weeping and gnaſhing of teeth. <hi>Here</hi> we are in Gods chamber of Preſence, that we may be brought into his preſence and chamber of ioy, whence we ſhall neuer bee ſhut out. Let vs then while the houſe of the Lord is eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, encourage one another, ſaying; <hi>Let vs goe vp to the mountaine of the Lord, to the houſe of the God of Iacob, and he will teach vs of his wayes, and wee will walke in his pathes,</hi> Iſa. 2.<note place="margin">Iſa. 2.2.3.</note> The Temple was Chriſts walke, as we find in theſe words: <hi>And Ieſus walked in the Temple, in Salomons Porch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Amongſt the <hi>Iewes</hi> the <hi>Temple</hi> was had in much reuerence,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chryſ, in Act.</hi> 6.14. Ier. 7.4. Act. 4.1. <hi>Bar.</hi> Ioh. 12.20, Act. 8.27. <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 11. <hi>Ant. c. vlt.</hi>
               </note> &amp; it was held a great honour to liue neere vnto it; theyr common cry was, <hi>The Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord,</hi> Ier. 7. The <hi>Temple</hi> had a captaine, <hi>Act.</hi> 4. as afterwardes Souldiers called <hi>Templarij,</hi> dwelling neere to the Temple, Knights of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> inſtituted <hi>Anno</hi> 1230. The Gentiles came to worſhip at the Temple, as that <hi>Eunuch</hi> of great authority vnder <hi>Candace</hi> Queene of the <hi>Ethiopians,</hi> Act. 8. and <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great;<note place="margin">2. Mac. 3.3, 35,</note> 
               <hi>Seleucus</hi> King of Aſia, <hi>Heliodorus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſ. Gor. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Antiochus</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers mentioned by <hi>Gorionides.</hi> Famous haue been the temple of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> the temple of <hi>Bellona,</hi>
               <note place="margin">M. Purch. in Pilg</note> hauing ſixe thouſand ſeruants a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>out it in <hi>Cappadocia;</hi> the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:986:16"/>of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> in <hi>Morimena</hi> with three thouſand vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries: at <hi>Carrhae</hi> they had the Temple of the <hi>Moone:</hi> at <hi>Taxilla</hi> a temple of the <hi>Sunne:</hi> at <hi>Athens</hi> they had a temple of <hi>Mercie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> cauſing a decree to bee made, that they which fled thither for ſuccour, might not be pulled away from thence. Such a Sanctuarie was the Temple of <hi>Theſeus;</hi> ſuch an immunity was tranſlated vnto the Temples of Chriſtians, to <hi>Abbies,</hi> and <hi>Monaſteries,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> when Princes had dedicated their names vnto <hi>Chriſt;</hi> prouiding by lawes, that whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhould violently draw away any from thence, they ſhould incurre the crime of treaſon; which was the cauſe, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Alaricus</hi> the King of the <hi>Gothes</hi> had ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſo many as fledde vnto the great Church of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> were through a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull worke of God preſerued: But abuſes hauing hence growne, and the Church &amp; Common-wealth iniuried, theſe are in many places abrogated; when ſeruants hence tooke occaſion to bee diſobedient, and vndutifull; vnconſcionable debters defrauded their creditors; thieues encreaſed, and that was vere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, <hi>Nullos tam ſaepe ad Eccleſiae aſylum ſugere, quàm qui nec Deum, nec Eccleſiam curabant;</hi> None more vſually and often fledde to the Sanctuary of the Church, then they that cared neyther for God nor the Church. The Temples of our times are for prayer, preaching, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the Sacraments, and ſo <hi>Sanctuaries for troubled ſoules,</hi> who deſire to bee fed with the ſincere milke of the word; wherein not onely the Lambe may wade, but the Lyon may ſwimme. <hi>Chriſt</hi> honoured the Temple with his walke in <hi>Salomons</hi> Porch. His
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:986:16"/>paſſion was neere, and as it were at the dore; therefore he walked in the Porch, in <hi>Salomons</hi> porch, where ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices were offered: that we might much more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent thoſe places, where there is a remembrance of his offering vp of himſelfe once for all. In <hi>Salomons</hi> Porch, becauſe there often <hi>Salomon</hi> vſed to pray: or it is called <hi>Salomons</hi> Porch, becauſe it was made in i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation of that; the length whereof was twenty cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bites, and the bredth thereof ten cubites,<note place="margin">1. Kin. 6.3.</note> 1. <hi>King.</hi> 6. Here he walked, ſhewing that ſometimes a man may retire and reſt himſelfe, but not ſo that he ruſt; for hee tooke occaſion by walking,<note place="margin">Aret:</note> to offer himſelfe to the oppoſitions of his Aduerſaries. <hi>Ioſephus</hi> notes, that the Temple had foure Porches: the firſt, for all generally, except menſtruous women: the ſecond, for the <hi>Iewes</hi> and their wiues: the third, for the onely Males of the <hi>Iewes:</hi> the fourth, for thoſe that brought the <hi>Prieſts</hi> robes. This <hi>Porch</hi> of <hi>Herods</hi> Temple is called Beautiful, where the lame ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was aſking almes of them, that entred into the Temple:<note place="margin">Act. 3.2.</note> 
               <hi>Act.</hi> 3. A fitte ſpectacle, <hi>teaching</hi> men to bee mercifull to ſuch, who themſelues come to craue mercy from God, and to reſpect theſe whom God placeth as Porters of his Court; <hi>teaching</hi> vs to open our wounds vnto God,<note place="margin">Chryſ. hom. <hi>28.</hi> ad Pop. Antioch</note> as they open theirs vnto vs. The <hi>beauty</hi> of this Porch is deſcribed by <hi>Ioſephus, Salmeron, Baronius, Ribera:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſ. <hi>6.</hi> de bel: Iud. c. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> Gods houſe is beautifull and amiable, therefore did <hi>Dauid</hi> long and faint after it; preferring one dayes being here, before a thouſand elſe-where, wiſhing ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be a dore-keeper in the houſe of God, then to dwell in the tents of wickedneſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.10.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84. <hi>And Ieſus
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:986:17"/>walked in the Temple, in Salomons Porch. Wiſdome</hi> wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in the houſe of the Wiſe man; whence wee may learne, <hi>That it is a fitte thing for Chriſtians often to frequent Gods houſe, his Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſts action herein may be our inſtruction.<note place="margin">Doctr.</note> 8, daies after his birth, <hi>hee was brought into the Temple,</hi> Luc. 2, to ſuffer circumciſion according to the Law: When hee grew and waxed ſtrong in Spirite, and was twelue yeeres old,<note place="margin">Lu. 2.27. v. 40.41.46.</note> 
               <hi>He was in the Temple, ſitting in the midſt of the Doctors, both hearing them, and aſking them queſtions;</hi> not to learne of them, but to inſtruct them: as he was man, he hearkned vnto them; as hee was God,<note place="margin">Orig:</note> hee oppoſed and anſwered them: Hee ſo aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and anſwered,<note place="margin">Eed:</note> that all that heard him were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhed at his vnderſtanding and anſweres. He taught and preached the Goſpell of the Kingdome in the <hi>Synagogues,</hi> Mat. 4.23. Hee taught dayly in the <hi>Temple,</hi>
               <note place="margin">v. 47.</note> Luk. 19.47. <hi>Earely</hi> in the morning he came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine into the Temple, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8.2. Hee <hi>euer</hi> taught in the Synagogue, and in the Temple, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 18.20. Heere he walked in the Temple. This was the walke of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid;</hi> As for me I will come into thy houſe in the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of thy mercy, and in thy feare will I worſhip to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thy holy Temple,<note place="margin">Pſalm: 5.7.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5. We tooke ſweete counſell together, and <hi>walked</hi> vnto the houſe of God in company,<note place="margin">Pſil. 55.14.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55. I was glad when they ſayde vnto me;<note place="margin">Pſalm. 122.1.</note> Let vs goe into the <hi>houſe</hi> of the Lord, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 122. The <hi>Apoſtles</hi> continued dayly with one accord in the <hi>Temple,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 2.46.</note> Act. 2. <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> went vp toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into the temple, at the houre of prayer, being the ninth houre,<note place="margin">Act 3.1.</note> Act. 3.1. <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> together went
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:986:17"/>to prepare the Paſſeouer,<note place="margin">Luc: 22 8. Ioh: 18 16</note> 
               <hi>Luk.</hi> 22. <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> went together into the Palace of the high Prieſt, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 18. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> ranne both together towards <hi>Chriſts</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchcre, <hi>Iohn</hi> 20.<note place="margin">Ioh: 20, 4</note> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> were ſent together to <hi>Samaria,</hi> when it had receiued the word of God, <hi>Act.</hi> 8. <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> anſwered the Councell boldly,<note place="margin">Act: 8 14</note> Whether it be right in the ſight of God, to hearken vnto you more then vnto God, iudge yee,<note place="margin">Act: 4, 19.</note> 
               <hi>Act.</hi> 4. <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> are yoked together; the old and young, that the young might be inſtructed and guided by the old. He leadeth his fellow to the <hi>Temple.</hi> An <hi>Angel</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Apoſtles, Go, ſtand and ſpeake in the temple to the people all the words of this life; &amp; when they heard that, they entred into the Temple earely in the morning and taught,<note place="margin">Act: 5.21</note> 
               <hi>Act.</hi> 5. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas</hi> went into the Synagogue on the Sabbath day, and ſate downe, <hi>Act.</hi> 13. <hi>Paul</hi> prayed in the Temple,<note place="margin">Act: 13.14 Act: 22.17</note> and was in a traunce, <hi>Act.</hi> 22. The <hi>Church</hi> is not for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular but religious offices. <hi>Anna</hi> a Propheteſſe, the daughter of <hi>Phanuel,</hi> a widdow of about foureſcore &amp; foure yeares, departed not from the temple,<note place="margin">Baſ: lib. <hi>2.</hi> de Bapt: quaeſt: <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> but ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued God with faſtings and praiers night and day, <hi>Luk.</hi> 2. <hi>Theodoſius</hi> went to all the places of praier he could. In theſe <hi>Temples,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luc: 2.37 <hi>Ruff: l:</hi> 2, <hi>ca:</hi> 33</note> and the true profeſſors (which are members hereof) God dwelleth and walketh in them, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. <hi>And Ieſus walked in the Temple.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor: 6.16</note>
            </p>
            <p>A iuſt <hi>cenſure</hi> this may be then of any, who deſpiſe or abuſe temples:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vſe.</hi> 1.</note> we hold not <hi>an inherent holineſſe in the places;</hi> &amp; that priuate praiers are bettered,<note place="margin">Wolfius in <hi>2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Re: <hi>12.</hi> ex Tertull:</note> when vttered within a conſecrated circle: <hi>Chriſt</hi> is our ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike temple; and by him whereſoeuer our praiers
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:986:18"/>are made in ſpirit and truth, they are alike acceptable to God; yet God <hi>eſpecially</hi> hath choſen theſe places to himſelfe. This <hi>Action</hi> of our Sauiour warranteth our aſſemblies in Churches: for, though <hi>Abraham</hi> made his couenant in the open wilderneſſe,<note place="margin">Gen. 21.21.27. Gen. 24.63.</note> 
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 21; &amp; <hi>Izhak</hi> praied in the fields, <hi>Gen.</hi> 24; and it is vncertaine what places <hi>Adam, Abel, Enos, Seth</hi> had to worſhip in: yet God hath now marked out his houſes, and they muſt be frequented. <hi>Chriſt</hi> came to this Temple after it had been prophaned,<note place="margin">Ioſ. l. 15.</note> and re-edefied for popular vaine glorie; and he that forbare not to imploy the <hi>water pots</hi> of the Iewiſh and ſuperſtitious purification, in the worke of his gracious miracle,<note place="margin">Ioh. 2.6.7.</note> 
               <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2, auoyded not the <hi>Iewiſh</hi> Temple: <hi>Why</hi> then doe ſo many ſeeke to pull downe the Temples and Churches of <hi>Chriſtians?</hi> from a <hi>ſwelling</hi> they are fallen to a ſhrinking in the ſinews; from ful-fed bodies, to a pining; ſo that <hi>vix faucibus haerent;</hi> ſcarce doe the ſtones in many of our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches hang together, they haue ſuſtained a long pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for their exceſſe. <hi>Simoniacall</hi> Patrons ſell pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations to our <hi>Churches;</hi> heyres to <hi>Iudas,</hi> whoſe La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine goeth no farther then <hi>Quid dabis:</hi> They enquire of the purſe of a man, not of his vertues; ſelling <hi>oxen, ſheepe, doues;</hi> all Church-preferments they haue of their owne, or are put in truſt with by others, to thoſe who cannot feede the flocke committed to their charge; or if they doe feede them, it is with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempered and often poiſonous foode. A ſinne now become <hi>vulnus cancroſum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amb.</note> a wound that hath a canker in it, and crept along through many ioyntes, and requireth <hi>ignitum ferrum,</hi> a hote
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:986:18"/>coulter or ſharpe ſword; the extremity of ciuill puniſhment. Leſt as before the comming of Chriſt in the fleſh,<note place="margin">Aug. de Ciu. Dei. l. <hi>2,</hi> c. <hi>19</hi>
               </note> the Romane Common wealth by little and little being changed, <hi>Ex pulcherrima &amp; optima, peſſima ac flagitioſiſſima facta eſt:</hi> So the Common wealth of <hi>England,</hi> and Chriſtianity, by buing the charge of ſoules before the ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt, of a moſt religious and well ordered Common wealth, will become irreligious and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane. <hi>The Eagle-clawed Church-robber,</hi> ſeeth a farre off a little portion remayning to the Church, and will ſo are at this by all politique inuentions, though hee take but a coale to fire his neſt. Theſe <hi>Locuſts</hi> nibble at that which the <hi>Palmer-worme</hi> hath left; worſe then <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> who had their diet with <hi>Pharaoh</hi> in the dearth, that they might not ſell their land, <hi>Gen.</hi> 47: they muſt haue to their heapes of ill <hi>gotten,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 47.22.</note> and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rablie <hi>kept</hi> goods, an <hi>Impropriate</hi> Tithe, which is moſt improper for any but the Church; though the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter and his family ſterue. Are not theſe <hi>ſnares</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, when hauing co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted ſpirituall theft, they are ſo followed by Gods hand into their houſes, which receiue ſuch ſtollen goods, that <hi>Reuenge ſhaketh the foundation of them for ſinne, and they in themſelues and theirs are vſually puniſhed.</hi> The <hi>ſcornefull Atheiſt</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſeth the calling of the Teachers of our Temples; ſcorning Prieſts, whoſe ſpirituall ſacrifice of praier, God accepteth as well as he did incenſe in the old law; and like railing <hi>Rabſhakehs</hi> ſeeke to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſport in blaſpheming the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> by ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in pieces his Meſſengers, in their <hi>drunken,</hi> laſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uious
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:986:19"/>raging diſcourſes, where they <hi>foame</hi> out their owne ſhame; not being terrified by the examples of <hi>Ieroboams</hi> withered hand; two <hi>Captaines</hi> and their fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties fired from Heauen; forty two <hi>chidren</hi> torne in pieces by wilde Beares; <hi>Corath</hi> and his Complices deuoured by the earth; <hi>Miriam</hi> a woman, ſtrucken with a leproſie for abuſing the Lords ſeruants. The Lord hath and will make good his promiſe to <hi>Leui; Bleſſe Lord his ſubſtance, and accept the worke of his hands;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 33.11.</note> 
               <hi>ſmite through the loines of them that riſe againſt him, and of them that hate him, that they riſe not againe,</hi> Deut. 33. They that haue honoured the Temple haue been honoured;<note place="margin">Eccl. 50.</note> 
               <hi>Simon</hi> the ſon of <hi>Onias</hi> repairing the Temple, <hi>how</hi> was he honoured in the midſt of the people? he was as the <hi>Morning</hi>-ſtarre in the midſt of a cloud, and as the <hi>Moone</hi> at the full; as the <hi>Sunne</hi> ſhining vpon the Temple of the moſt high; and as the <hi>Rainebow</hi> giuing light in the bright cloudes; as the <hi>flowre</hi> of Roſes in the ſpring of the yeare, as <hi>Lilies</hi> by the riuers of waters, and as the branches of the <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kincence</hi> tree in the time of Summer, as <hi>fire</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe in the Cenſer, and as a veſſell of beaten gold, ſet with all manner of pretious ſtones; as a faire <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue</hi> tree budding forth, and as a <hi>Cypreſſe</hi> tree which groweth vp to the clouds: <hi>Simon Magus</hi> that thought ſo baſely of the beſt gifts belonging to Gods Temple, hee, <hi>on the other ſide</hi> hath been put to open ſhame, and his <hi>necke</hi> broken. Thus they that ſtand for holy things dedicated to God, haue ſtood and flouriſhed; but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue periſhed for abuſing the <hi>place</hi> of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or <hi>men</hi> of the temple,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aq.</hi> 2.2. <hi>q.</hi> 99.2.3.</note> or <hi>things</hi> dedicated to holy
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:986:19"/>vſes in the Temple: Such thinke this to be no ſinne now, becauſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> is not preſent with a whip for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as hee was in <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> but they may feare a more terrible whip hereafter, without reſtitution and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition; and learne of <hi>Ieſus</hi> to defend the Temple, &amp; frequent it. <hi>Ieſus walked in the Temple, in Salomons Porch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How may this encourage vs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 2.</note> who haue <hi>Churches</hi> and <hi>Chappels</hi> for our frequent and religious aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies: <hi>God</hi> is not included in any one place: Hee is euery where by his <hi>power</hi> and operation, by his <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> and viſion, by his <hi>immenſitie</hi> and incircumſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; he is in the <hi>humanity</hi> of Chriſt by an hypoſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call vnion; In his <hi>Saints</hi> by loue, in <hi>Heauen</hi> by his Maieſty, in the <hi>Church</hi> by an eſpeciall aſſiſtance and direction; hee is euery where, whole filling Heauen and earth; his power being preſent,<note place="margin">Aug. l. <hi>7.</hi> de Ciu. Dei. c. <hi>30.</hi> Cyp. l. de vanit. Idolorum.</note> his nature not abſent. All the world is his Temple; <hi>yet</hi> muſt wee not vpon this pretence auoide <hi>Churches,</hi> as <hi>Ieroboam</hi> diſſwaded from ſet times and places of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,<note place="margin">Ioſ. Ant. l. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>3.8.</hi>
               </note> becauſe <hi>God</hi> heareth euery where; he <hi>eſpecially</hi> affordeth his <hi>preſence</hi> in thoſe places, which he calleth his <hi>houſes;</hi> and therefore <hi>Cain</hi> for his murther, not da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to come to the place appointed for the ſeruice of God, is ſaid to go out from the preſence of the Lord, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4: And when <hi>Ionas</hi> is ſayde to flie from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lord, <hi>Ion.</hi> 1, <hi>Aben Ezra</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Gen. 4.16. Ion. 1.3.</note> that hee fled from that place where the Prophets ſtood, and offered themſelues to be ſent of God, when he ſhould commaund them: If God bee in the midſt of <hi>two</hi> or <hi>three,</hi> gathered together in his name, how much more
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:986:20"/>gratiouſly is hee with the multitudes of godly, whoſe prayers are as <hi>thunderclaps,</hi> or the roaring of the ſea. Such <hi>oratories</hi> doe wee enioy, founded by <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Baſ:</note> as well as any of Romiſh Religion: what was it for them in Popery to build Churches, or repayre them.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Campians</hi> ſpeech at the funerall of Sir <hi>T: White.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>In maxima rerum vilitate, &amp; multorum opibus adiuti,</hi> in a time of great cheapneſſe of euerie thing, and helped with the riches of many men? It is a <hi>ſlander</hi> that our Faith or <hi>Credo</hi> pulleth downe thoſe Churches, which their <hi>Pater Noſter</hi> founded: Their claime is falſe, to bee <hi>founders</hi> of Churches. <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> the great built Churches before Popery was hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched: <hi>Charles</hi> the great,<note place="margin">B. Bad: in Exod.</note> Schooles of Diuinity, and Vniuerſities in <hi>Germany, France, Italy,</hi> not for Popery, but for the Bible to bee taught in; and the <hi>Britaines</hi> ancient Inhabiters of this nation, had their Churches and Temples, and yet no Popery: If <hi>they</hi> built or repayred our Churches,<note place="margin">Bede:</note> we may frequent them, being ſwept and purged, and reformed. Some zealous pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors the Lord rayſeth vp, to adde more vnto theſe, and to vphold thoſe already built, that they may bee dedicated houſes vnto God; eſpecially hauing ſo Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious a Leader as our <hi>Salomon,</hi> who daily encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth and commandeth to ſuch charitable works, <hi>The Lord his God hauing now giuen him reſt on euery ſide,</hi> 1. <hi>King.</hi> 5: to theſe we call, as to <hi>Fountaines</hi> of the water of life, that men would taſte, and ſee that the Lord is good,<note place="margin">1. King. 5.4.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34: We ſay come hither <hi>old men</hi> and Fathers,<note place="margin">Pſal, 34 4.</note> and learne of <hi>Simeon</hi> to ſing a <hi>Nunc dimittis;</hi> Be not loth to depart in peace: Come hither, <hi>young men</hi> and brethren, <hi>Wee will teach you the feare of the Lord.</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:986:20"/>We here ſing: <hi>Praiſe the Lord all yee Nations,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 127.1.</note> 
               <hi>praiſe him all yee people.</hi> To this end is this <hi>Chappell this day dedicated vnto God;</hi> and the lawfulneſſe of dedication we haue ſeene. We may reioice now, and be glad in the Lord; It will become vs wel to be thankfull, and to teſtifie our thankefulneſſe by continuing our care in our ſeuerall places.</p>
            <q>Ne longo ſermone morer tua tempor a Praeſul:</q>
            <p>Reuerend and Honourable <hi>Father</hi> of this Dioceſſe, Be as hetherto you haue been to this religious towne, a faithfull Patron to Church and Schoole; as <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to Epheſus, Titus</hi> to <hi>Crete, Polycarpus</hi> to <hi>Smyrna, Paulinus</hi> to <hi>Nola, Primaſius</hi> to <hi>Vtica, Eucherius</hi> to <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Chryſoſtome</hi> to <hi>Conſtantinople, Cyprian</hi> to <hi>Carthage, Ambroſe</hi> to <hi>Millaine, Auſtin</hi> to <hi>Hippo:</hi> This <hi>towne</hi> yet flouriſheth in many bleſſings; and ſo it wil, if faction and ſchiſme preuayle not againſt the peace of it.</p>
            <p>Worthy and carefull <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>M. Iohn Nichols, M. Richard Winn,</hi> then the two Bailiues, both preſent, and ſome of the 12 Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and 24 Counſellours. A Sermon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of new Bailiues.</note> Be you with your <hi>Brethren</hi> truſty <hi>Guardians</hi> of the Schooles and Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers; defend their foundation, reuenues, priuiledges: The <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> defendeth the ſcholler with his ſword, and the ſcholler defendeth the Magiſtrate with his penne. Let <hi>Learning</hi> be countenanced by you, and the learned ſhall praiſe you. I ſhall hereafter giue you a more ample <hi>charge</hi> out of another Text of Scripture; where you ſhall ſee that you muſt giue an account of your office to the God of Gods.</p>
            <p>Prouident and induſtrious <hi>Maſters</hi> of this Schoole, ſo teach your Schollers, that they may haue this teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony which <hi>Cyprian</hi> gaue Chriſtians;<note place="margin">Cyp: ad Iubaia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</note> 
               <hi>Veniunt vt
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:986:21"/>diſcant, Diſcunt vt viuant,</hi> They come to learne, and learne here the Art of liuing well: All your <hi>Art</hi> is now reduced into two words, <hi>Deus</hi> &amp; <hi>Rex:</hi> Inſtruct them to <hi>Feare God and honour the King;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Intus ſi recte, ne labora.</note> and then the Motto of your Schoole, may be engrauen vpon your conſciences; <hi>We deſerue not iuſt cenſures, and paſſe by vniuſt:</hi> Be <hi>content</hi> with that you haue, countenance <hi>none</hi> to challenge that which is the portion of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: If <hi>they</hi> pull from the Church that which is due, and pretend to <hi>bring</hi> it hither; it is like <hi>Iudas</hi> proiect, that would not haue <hi>Chriſts</hi> body annointed, but the poore relieued: <hi>It is an hon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ring of the members, and vncouering of the head:</hi> That <hi>little</hi> which they take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way (and but little all is left) eateth, as we ſee, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their wealth, who ſeeke to robbe <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>Schoole:</hi> Let your diligent <hi>labours</hi> make ſuch, that may defend you from vniuſt wrongs; and then, as <hi>Herod</hi> the great, though at home,<note place="margin">Ioſeph Antiq: l. <hi>16.6.</hi>
               </note> was moſt vnhappy in his wife and children, yet abroad was moſt happy for his friends, acquaintance, and other proſperity; ſo though you may haue ſome who ſeeke your hurt, being neere; yet others who are imployed farre from you, may defend you.</p>
            <p>Young <hi>Plants</hi> of this conſecrated Vineyard, I ſay to you, as <hi>Salomon</hi> to his young man: <hi>Remember now your creator in the dayes of your youth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 12.1.</note> Eccl. 12.</p>
            <q>Dum vires annique ſinunt,—</q>
            <p>While ſtrength and yeeres ſuffer you, Be diligent and conſtant in preparing your ſelues to be hereafter or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments of the Church and common wealth. Now is your <hi>Harueſt;</hi> Let your Schoole be as it is called
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:986:21"/>
               <hi>Ludus literarius,</hi> a place wherein you take pleaſure to learne, rather then a paine; <hi>Redeeme</hi> the time, the daies are euill; <hi>Life is ſhort,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hippocrates.</note> 
               <hi>Art is long.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let vs all <hi>Beloued, heare the end of all:</hi> Feare God, and keepe his commandements, for this is the whole duty of man: All of vs muſt appeare,<note place="margin">Eccl. 12 13.</note> where we muſt giue a reckoning of our Stewardſhip, as <hi>yeſterday di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinely we were admoniſhed.</hi>
               <note place="margin">In a Sermon by the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Biſhop, in S. <hi>Chaddes</hi> Church.</note> Let vs performe all duty to our Temples; Let vs remember that wee were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed to bee <hi>Temples</hi> of the holy Ghoſt: <hi>Holineſſe</hi> becommeth Gods Temples: If we labour here truely to bee <hi>holy,</hi> then hereafter wee ſhall bee truly <hi>happy;</hi> and being receiued into the holy <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> which is aboue, and onely free, and the mother of vs all, wee ſhall ſing <hi>Hoſanna</hi> the ſong of children; <hi>Halleluiah,</hi> the ſong of the Elders; <hi>Holy, Holy, Holy,</hi> Lord God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, the ſong of <hi>Cherubims</hi> &amp; <hi>Seraphims;</hi> and ſhall for euer liue in glory with the <hi>Father,</hi> the <hi>Sonne,</hi> and the <hi>Spirit:</hi> To which <hi>Frinitie</hi> we ſhall aſcribe prayſe and power in a vnitie, for euer and euer: So be it, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
